Guide to the Ed Wood, Jr. collection, 1966-2006.
Wood, Ed Jr. collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ed Wood, Jr. collection, 1966-2006.
7779
Wood, Edward D.(Edward Davis)
Books, magazines, print outs, placards, poster, DVD.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Pulp novels written anonymously and under various pseudonyms of the legendary psycho-sexual author and film-maker, Ed Wood, Jr., collected by pulp scholar Robert Legault (1950 to 2008). In addition, magazines, reference materials, posters and other ephemera; and a DVD about Ed Wood.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Edward Davis Wood, Jr. (October 10, 1924 to December 10, 1978), better known as Ed Wood, was an American screenwriter, director, producer, actor, author, and editor, who made a number of low-budget genre films and published pulp novels under various names. Ed Wood's fiction is as strange, idiosyncratic and out of step with his times and mores as his infamous movies. His novels inter-splice erotic segments with lengthy philosophical, sociological and psychological discourse. Rudolph Grey's biography "Nightmare of Ecstasy: The Life and Art of Edward D. Wood, Jr." (1992) and Tim Burton's biopic "Ed Wood," which earned two Academy Awards, brought attention to his life and work. He died in 1978 of an alcohol-induced heart attack and has since achieved cult status.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Pulp novels written anonymously and under various pseudonyms of the legendary psycho-sexual author and film-maker, Ed Wood, Jr., collected by pulp scholar Robert Legault (1950 to 2008). In addition, magazines, reference materials, posters and other ephemera.
Also, an original one sheet poster for the 1953 film, "Glen or Glenda?" directed by Ed Wood, Jr. in his feature film debut. Originally titled "I Changed My Sex," the film has maintained a solid cult following over the decades despite its poor reviews due to Wood's decidedly distinctive style and z-budget production values. The aim of the film's producer, George Weiss, was to capitalize on the story Christina Jorgensen, who in 1952 became the first man widely known to undergo sex reassignment surgery. The film's first half guides the viewer down a crooked path that includes multiple narration techniques, BDSM (bondage/discipline/sadomasochist) pornography, and a buffalo stampede in order to convey a story about a man named Glen who wishes to become a transvestite, struggling to gain acceptance from his girlfriend. The second half, added largely at the demand of the distributor to include sex change in the content, is about a pseudohermaphrodite named Alan who fights his way through World War II in women's underwear, finally returning from the conflict to have the surgery he/she has always desired.
Also, a DVD of an episode of "The Incredibly Strange Film Show," volume 3, on Ed Wood, featuring interviews with Wood's colleagues and clips from his films "Glen or Glenda?", "Bride of the Monster," "Plan 9 From Outer Space," "Revenge of the Dead," and "The Bride and the Beast." Also included in the DVD is his film "The Sinister Urge."
SUBJECTS
Names:
Wood, Edward D., Jr. (Edward Davis), 1924-1978.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Collecting Program: Human Sexuality Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Novels
  - Black Lace Drag By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1963; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Raven Books, North Hollywood
    [Wood’s first novel]
  - Killer in Drag By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1965; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Imperial Books/Star News Co., Union City, NJ
    [same as Black Lace Drag (Raven, 1963), Wood’s first novel. Also printed as Black Lace Drag (Private Edition, 1967) and The Twilight Land (Europa, 1967) credited to Sheri Blue.]
  - The Homosexual Generation By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Ken Worthy, 1965; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    Publisher: imperial Books/L.S. Publications Corp., New York
    [purported socio-sexual study of the leanings of the current generation. Generally derogatory in nature. Page 105: "A fair sample of what is happening to the man-woman relationship can be seen in the movie, ‘The Knack – and How to Get it.’ Like, ‘Goodbye, Charley,’ and ‘Some Like It Hot,’ this is another thinly disguised homosexual movie in which a young girl goes about begging one of three young men to rape her. The men show no interest whatsoever, and the homosexual element is brought out clearly when the leading character says of another male, ‘I want him to come here and live with us. His name is Ricky. He’s beautifully big – six foot three – and he can teach both of us some tricks.’ All the male characters in the movie have hair curling around their collars; all wear their hair brushed forward in a pompadour and all are very obviously interested only in males to the bewilderment of the girl who is trying to get herself raped." Page 174: "So there is a ‘cure’ for homosexuality – and it rests entirely with the parents!"] I personally think this questionable whether or not its Wood
  - Mask of Evil By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Charlene White, 1966; Pages: 157 (Box 1)
    Publisher: First Niter Books, Inc., Buffalo
    Cover art by Eric Stanton; also includes an interior advertisement for Stanton's "Stantoons."
    [Page 94: "The intruder was going deeper, penetrating further and further into her sensitive, exquisite tenderness. She moaned and moved, trying to escape the sweet pain, yet now quite wanting not to do so. Her movements only made the pain go deeper. ‘Oh, no! No.’ She moaned. ‘Stop. Please stop. Don’t stop! It’s good. It hurts, Ohh-h-h-h-h!’ The pressure on her became unbearably good. Her senses were reeling. Colors were whirling and swirling under her closed eyelids. Then suddenly, sweetly, inexplicably, she was past the pain and was moving and twisting in harmony with the youth. Suddenly, she knew she had to scream. Her lips parted without volition and a harsh, rough sound poured from her..At the same time the young man’s breathing became jagged, cutting litany. Infinity became finite and stood still."] read to give summary
  - Orgy of the Dead By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., intro by Forrest J. Ackerman, 1966; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Greenleaf Classics, Inc., San Diego
    Photo Illustrated by R. Charleton Wilson (b&w)
    [novelization of the film by the same name, scripted by Ed Wood, directed by A. C. Stephen (Stephen Apostolof). Cover art done by adult paperback master Robert Bonfils. The wolfman on the cover is not actually in the book, but only in the film. Illustrated with stills from the film.] add compiled info/summarize/excerpt
  - Parisian Passions By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: J. X. Williams (on cvr only, inside TP is Wood), 1966; Pages: 191 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Corinth Publications, San Diego
    [cover reads by J. X. Williams, a house name for Corinth, however the inside title page states Wood’s real name. Original title was reported as 69 Rue Pigalle. The story follows Parisian Inspector Goulet tracking down the killer of a number of strippers on the Rue Morgue. He brings in Texas man Sherriff Buck Rhodes and female impersonator Lorraine Peters for assistance. Page 79: "Buck poured his glass full from the second bottle of wine. It was apparent from the tensions in the room that the unruly, sex-crazed mob wanted action and they wanted it now. They had been kept waiting too long already. They hadn’t come down to the cellar just to sit around contemplating their own belly buttons. Their whole idea was to contemplate someone else’s belly button."] Eric Stanton cvr art?
  - Side-Show Siren By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1966; Pages: 190 (Box 1)
    [Rudolph Grey detailed: "When Karl the Abominable Snowman escapes from a carnival, a series of gruesome murders ensues. Change from the original title Naked Bones as more marketable for the paperback trade, Side-Show Siren is possibly the first of Wood’s carnival novels. It resembles films like The Ape (with Boris Karloff, Monogram, 1940) and Circus of Horrors (AIP, 1960). The character of Jinx Dixon, a cowboy sharpshooter, is modeled after Wood’s close friend, Kenne Duncan." One-time Republic Pictures contract actor, Kenne "Horsecock" Duncan was, according to Grey, "known and billed as ‘the meanest man in the movies.’"]
  - A Half World By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Michael Sharon, 1967; Pages: 159 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Pad Library, Agoura, CA
  - Black Lace Drag By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Private Edition Books, Canoga Park
    [1967 reprint of 1963 Raven Books Black Lace Drag, Wood’s first book. Verso of title page claims "first printing 1967".]
  - Bloodiest Sex Crimes in History By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Spenser and West, 1967; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Pad Library/Nite Time, Agoura, CA
    [in the style of Spenser and West, "sexological" studies of vampirism, murder, necrophilia, prostitution, and contains a glossary of terminology. Page 61: "This is not to suggest that ALL or even MOST morticians are Necrophiles. It merely supposes that if one is inclined toward the Necrophile practice – the choice of being a Mortician is logical."] read, excerpt, what is up with catalog numbers corresponding to other pub. companies?
  - Confessions of a Hollywood Starlet By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Spenser and West, 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Cougar Publications, Los Angeles
    [Not mentioned elsewhere in Wood literature, this book contains many Woodian hallmarks, i.e. gratuitous ellipses and Hollywood sleaze, however the writing is slightly more sober than usual. The story concerns casting couch shenanigans, with character names such as Jake Palerack, Wolfgang von Klienshimdt, Fritz Dykeman, and Beverly Fuller.]
  - Death of a Transvestite By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    [the follow-up to Black Lace Drag, concerns contract killer Glen/Glenda on death row who demands to be allowed to die in drag. Told in a Gothic epistolary style via clippings, confessions, etc. Considered one of Wood’s finest works.] excerpt
  - Devil Girls By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    [Rudolph Grey writes: "In the small town of Almanac, Texas, Sheriff Buck Rhodes tangles with drug smugglers and teenage gangs, including the wild girl gang, The Chicks. A series of sexual liaisons and violence culminate in their tragic end." David Hayes qualified, "Owing chiefly to the year it was printed, Devil Girls stands as the testament to Wood’s writing in the Golden Age. Low on smut, but high on intrigue and scandal, the novel moves along at a brisk pace and creates characters that are both believable and interesting (aside from Wood’s usual stereotypical bad girls)."]
  - Drag Trade By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 159 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Triumph News Co., Inc., Van Nuys
    [Page 38: "But come as it may, for the first time in his life he felt like a human being. Before, with only the panties and the half slip he hadn’t been quite sure. He knew he liked the feeling of the clothes then, but once he had dressed completely as a girl, he knew it was the life he must lead. None of their hair would ever grow to any length, but wigs took care of that small problem. And being young they taught him just how far his bust line should extend. He love sweaters, the soft cashmeres and angoras...and he liked to see the breasts sticking out in front of him...but for his size and age he was limited to the lines of a teenager."]
  - It Takes One to Know One By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 191 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Pad Library/Imperial, Agoura, CA
    [excerpt]
  - Security Risk By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    [Grey writes: "Espionage, Wood style, involving hard communists, sabotage at a movie set, and hard-loving, hard smoking and hard drinking Col. Harvey Tate." Hayes: "This is another classic case of Wood’s real-world experience (minus the freaky sex) shoved smack dab into a smut novel." The plot surrounds terrorists murdering employees at a government operated low-budget film company, much like Autonetics Aviation, a company Wood had briefly made films for in the past.]
  - Sex Life of the Alcoholic By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Johnny J., 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Griffon Enterprises/Nite Time Books, Beverly Hills
    [case histories of boozy sexual encounters, dedication reads: "To those anonymous booze-fighters whose stories are presented in these pages – and to the scores of others, likewise not to be named, who have helped in the preparation of this book. – Johnny J." Book topics include "Early Drinking and Introduction to Sex", "Alcohol as a Sexual Lubricant", "Breakdown of Sexual Inhibitions", "Rape, Incest and Homosexuality Through Release by Alcohol", and "Housewife Prostitution and Alcohol."]
  - Strange Sisters By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Sheri Blue, 1967; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Europa Books Limited/Pad Library, Los Angeles
    [this book is indicative of a bibliographical problem found elsewhere in both the Ed Wood Collection and in the greater adult paperback business. Due to the illegal nature of many publications, tax evasion, reusing old book components for new publications, and ties to more savage legal infractions, companies were constantly starting, collapsing and renaming themselves in a fly-by-night fashion. Therefore we find ourselves with situations like Strange Sisters which has a Pad Library ID# on the cover, yet on the verso of the title page we find the publication credit attributed to Europa Books Limited. Obscured by a fog of criminality it is quite difficult to know where one company ended and another began. It is highly likely that the amalgam of imprints were owned by only a few people. For instance, Michael Thevis of Pendulum was said to have owned 90% of all adult bookstores during the 1970s. Viceroy Books and Private Editions Books shared the same Canoga Park address. See also Bloodiest Sex Crimes in History and It Takes One To Know One for more confusion.]
  - Suburbia Confidential By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Emil Moreau, 1967; Pages: 159 (Box 1)
    [A collection of case histories as reported to Emil Moreau, "M. D." Beyond the basic concept, allegedly Wood and the book had nothing to do with the Apostolof film of 1966.]
  - The Twilight Land By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Sheri Blue, 1967; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    [another 1967 reprint of Wood’s Black Lace Drag this time under alternate title and pen name. David C. Hayes claims a 1965 edition of The Twilight Land exists as well, though he may be mistaken.]
  - Watts...After By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 191 (Box 1)
    [Follow-up to Watts...The Difference, more exploits with black nationalists and low-budget filmmakers] excerpt/summary
  - Watts...The Difference By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1967; Pages: 192 (Box 1)
    Cover art is signed but tough to read; looks like "Chad Collen"
    [a Watts riot exploitation piece, it’s rumored that Wood’s home was firebombed after the books release. Other stories include death threats from the Black Panthers. Alternate version is said to exist as Burn Baby Burn (1969) by Ray Jones] excerpt/summary
  - Bye Bye Broadie By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1968; Pages: 157 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Pendulum Publishers, Los Angeles
    Photo Illustrated (b&w)
    [another pictorial, this time with stills from a Image 4 motion picture production. Wood biographer Rudolph Grey summarized Broadie, "A peeping tom rapist spies on a group of young women making love in a boarding school. He approaches them and joins in on thethe action. The man-hating schoolmistress, Mrs. Grundy, discovers the orgy and beats the man to death with her cane. The headmistress then coerces the girls to assist her in burying the body in a nearby pet cemetery. After the burial, a hand appears out of the ground and grabs one of the young girls. The bloodied "corpse" smashes Mrs. Grundy with a shovel, sending her off into eternity. After another young girl falls victim to his revenge, the now blind young man staggers off toward the swamp water. Accompanying photos are only marginally related to the story." Page 105/6: "All any of them wanted to do was get the damned carcass in the ground and get the hell out of there. Time was against them! They had to make the new movement of time aid in their own advantage."]
  - Carnival Piece By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Kathleen Everett, 1968; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    [Kathleen Everett was in fact Wood’s wife’s maiden name. Akin to Side-Show Siren the novel follows a "murder-at-the-carnival" plot. Grey writes: "Imbroglios concerning carnivals, a murdered dancing girl and her stunning young blonde replacement who attracts the attentions of the local sheriff, the owner of the carnival and Mama Tate, a fat lesbian. Characters include Wheezy the Skeleton, who prefers wine to food; the Geek, another wino who bites the heads off snakes and chickens; Bertha the 450 pound fat woman; the tattoo man; the magician ("a ham bone lush"); the wolf man who "glues hair on his body everyday while he sniffs the glue and pops heroin in his veins"; and Matty, the female impersonator who does the half-man, half-woman act."]
  - For Love Or Money By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Arthur Windsor, 1968; Pages: 149 (Box 1)
    Publisher: B. B. Sales Co., New York, NY
    Photo Illustrated by Bill New (b&w)
    [For Love Or Money originally began as the novel The Sexecutives (1968) by Donald L. Westermier (pseudonym of Edward D. Wood, Jr.). Wood turned the novel into a script named For Love Or Money that was in turn realized by sexploitation director Don A. Davis. As was popular, the film was turned into a Foto-Reader which featured text opposite film stills. The For Love Or Money Foto-Reader is an abridged version of The Sexecutives, with much of Wood’s unique syntactical approaches excised, thus rendering, by most accounts, a truly bland affair.]
  - Hell Chicks By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: N. V. Jason, 1968; Pages: 188 (Box 1)
    Cover art signed "H"
    [Rudolph Grey wrote: "Ghosted under ‘N. V. Jason’, Hell Chicks, is one of Wood’s most crazed, anarchistic novels. The complete disregard for normal rules of grammar suggest that it was written in one sitting. Unleashed in distorted, alcoholic twists of consciousness, the novel takes girl gangs from his screenplays for The Violent Years and Fugitive Girls to the ne plus ultra of sex and violence. The Hell Chicks are twelve rough tough broads in black leather jackets. Their credo: ‘Rules are LAWS and LAWS were meant to be broken.’ Hopped up on grass and beer they roar across the countryside on their hogs, raping any man they can get their hands on. Pussy, Pisser, Prancer, Sissy, Syph, Boobie, Cherry and Flame meet their inevitable end in a climactic bloody showdown with the law." Page 82: "The boys of the Chain Gang hit from the north and the girls of the Hell Chicks screamed in from the south. Twenty-four cycles with split mufflers roared their tunes of terror, into the hearts and soul of every passerby. They gunned the exhaust...revved the motor...spit the back-fire flame and noise into anybody who dared brace them. They all screamed like banshees and the words of vulgar sexual atonement intermingled with the screaching of tires as they turned as if on a dime and giving nine cents change." As reported by David Hayes, Hell Chicks marks Wood’s turn to hardcore pornography.]
  - Purple Thighs By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1968; Pages: 156 (Box 1)
    [Hippie sexploitation, cover says "Originally titled Lost Souls Delivered", Wood’s personal acronym for LSD. Main characters Adam and Eve.] excerpt
  - Raped in the Grass By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1968; Pages: 157 (Box 1)
    [This Wood novelization of a "film" by D-M Productions, Los Angeles, was likely written from scratch and no film was ever produced. Raped in the Grass is a pre-Hearst/SLA Helsinki syndrome psycho-sexual fantasy. The book concerns two American girls who get captured by guerillas in a Central American country. A large amount of sexual and violent torture is unleashed by the guerillas on the girls who desperately want to leave. Yet, by the end of the pictorial, the American girls realize they have found a new home amidst the sexual degradation in Central America. "A guerilla band of near-wild men and one sadistic lesbian capture two young girls on a trip... a trip that either one of them will ever forget." Page 143: "Carlos, on the ground, as he came to, reached for his injured ear. For the moment, he thought he was back raping the girl on the grass. His ear hurt, his eyes opened. He looked at the makeshift table – to the ankles of his Leader, then he knew although his ass was in the grass, he was not with the broad. The Leader was. He needed another drink... ,He rolled over and could only lick at the remnants of his broken jug. ‘More tequila – more tit!’"]
  - Sex Museum By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Jason Nichols, 1968; Pages: 160 (Box 1)
    Publisher: Viceroy Books, Canoga Park
    [Sex Museum is a retelling of various sexual rites and occurrences throughout history. [Page 81: "The father of our country, the U.S.A., may very well have tried to be just that, the FATHER of our country! He certainly made one hell of an attempt at propagating the race of early Americans to a point where many a colonial mother locked their alluring daughter behind doors when they saw the young militia colonel approaching. George Washington, the first President of the new states of America was a ‘cock-smith’ from the word ‘GO.’"]
  - Sex Shrouds and Caskets By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1968; Pages: 187 (Box 1)
    [Writings on the intermingling of sex and religion. Page 113: "Harry TURNED the girls ON as he had done all of his adult life. But he TURNED THEM ON with a completely new, foolproof line. ‘The force of evil is within all of us! It is for me to turn that evil out of your souls.’ Then he would open the BOOK at random and read a short paragraph, then put in his own interpretation. None could deny his words because as so many of his predecessors, he was reading them from the BOOK, and that could not be wrong."]
  - The Erotic Spy By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Abbott Smith, 1968; Pages: 157 (Box 1)
    [Pendulum Pictorials was a series akin to the Olympic Foto-Reader, wherein text was accompanied by photo stills from a film. As far as the Pendulum Pictorials go, it is highly doubtful that any moving picture ever existed and rather the still photographs were taken with the purpose of illustrating the book. The Erotic Spy featured the character "The Gold Girl" who was also in the film Orgy of the Dead, played by Pat Barrington. A note from the Editor: "Gold Girl is one of the most exciting characters to have emerged from the world of fiction in recent years. Completely amoral, infinitely and diabolically clever, willing to use her voluptuous body in absolutely any way to achieve her ends, Gold Girl is, perhaps, fiction’s most formidable adversary since Superman...Because Gold Girl’s relations with everyone she met – men and women alike – are heavily weighted with sexual overtones, the film was produced exclusively for adult audiences."]
  - The Gay Underworld By: Edward D. Wood, Jr., 1968; Pages: 192 (Box 2)
    [Rudolph Grey writes: "Similar to Wood’s Drag Trade of 1967, with several episodes slightly rewritten.]
  - The Love of the Dead By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: V. N. Jensen, 1968; Pages: 156 (Box 2)
    [Page 66: "The [r]evulsion would last only a short time... Then there must be another dead partner...Soon there would never be the signs of revulsion again... Only hope...and the exercising of his demands."]
  - The Perverts By: Edward D. Wood, Jr. Pseudonym: Jason Nichols, 1968; Pages: 160 (Box 2)